{
  "filename": "2017-2018-HS-History-Bowl-Round-1-A-Set_formattedText.txt",
  "questions": [
    {
      "number": "1.2",
      "quarter": 1,
      "answer": "Dewey Defeats Truman",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "Prior to coining this three-word phrase, the organization that developed it controversially referred toone of its subjects as a “nincompoop”. An iconic image displaying this phrase shows a man traveling bytrain from Independence, Missouri to Washington DC. A forecast by Arthur Sears Henning inspired thisphrase, a prediction made after polls indicated a Democratic defeat in the 1948 election. For ten points,name this false headline published by the Chicago Daily Tribune."
    },
    {
      "number": "1.3",
      "quarter": 1,
      "answer": "Babylon (accept Whore of Babylon; accept Babylonian Captivity)",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "A ruler of this city has a dream in which he sees a statue with a gold head, a bronze belly, and clayfeet. A Biblical figure partially named for this city is described as sitting on top of a scarlet beast withseven heads and ten horns. The Book of Ezekiel was composed while Ezekiel was in this city, which namesa whore encountered in the Book of Revelation. The Book of Daniel tells of Nebuchadnezzar II, the rulerof, for ten points, what city where the Jews were held in a namesake period of captivity?"
    },
    {
      "number": "1.4",
      "quarter": 1,
      "answer": "Switzerland (accept Old Swiss Confederacy)",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "This modern day country obtained de facto independence from the Holy Roman Empire after theSwabian War. France obtained Burgundy shortly after Charles the Bold died fighting a force primarilyfrom this country at the Battle of Nancy. German Landsknechts imitated pike and halberd-wieldingmercenaries from this country, whose neutrality was affirmed during the Thirty Years War. For ten points,name this Alpine country with capital at Bern that remained neutral in both world wars."
    },
    {
      "number": "1.5",
      "quarter": 1,
      "answer": "George Friedrich Handel",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "This composer likely hired horn players from Bohemia for the premiere of a piece whose first suite,in F major, includes an “Adagio e staccato” movement. This composer included “La Paix” [la pay] in asuite for wind band written to celebrate the Treaty of Aix-La-Chapelle, and he included hornpipes in apiece written for a concert for King George I held on a barge on the Thames. For ten points, name thisGerman-born English composer of Music for the Royal Fireworks and Water Music."
    },
    {
      "number": "1.6",
      "quarter": 1,
      "answer": "Dole (accept Elizabeth Dole; accept Bob Dole)Page 1NHBB A-Set Bowl 2017-2018 Bowl Round 1",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "A politician with this surname campaigned with a Frankenstein doll that declared “You have nothingto fear with” that man. A woman with this surname won the Senate seat made available by the retirementof Jesse Helms; that woman with this married surname served as Secretary of Transportation underRonald Reagan and Secretary of Labor under George W. Bush. For ten points, give this surname sharedby North Carolina senator Elizabeth and a Kansas senator who lost the 1996 presidential election to BillClinton, Bob."
    },
    {
      "number": "1.7",
      "quarter": 1,
      "answer": "Hideki Tojo",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "This man said “I am very sorry it is taking me so long to die” after attempting suicide during hisarrest. The Imperial Rule Assistance Political Association was created by this man, who suggested notexecuting the pilots of the Doolittle Raid in fear of American retaliation. After being arrested, this manwas given a new pair of dentures which had the phrase “remember Pearl Harbor” written in Morse Code. For ten points, name this politician who served as Japan’s Prime Minister from 1941 to 1944."
    },
    {
      "number": "1.8",
      "quarter": 1,
      "answer": "Aristotle",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "This thinker’s concept of the “efficient cause” in the natural world was continued by his successor,Theophrastus. A graded scale of perfection established by this man to classify living organisms is knownas his “Great Chain of Being”. This philosopher, who was exiled by Eurymedon the Hierophant, wasaccused by Hagnothemis of poisoning his most famous pupil, Alexander the Great. For ten points, namethis Ancient Greek founder of the Lyceum and student of Plato."
    },
    {
      "number": "1.9",
      "quarter": 1,
      "answer": "Stamp Act of 1765",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "Andrew Oliver was tasked with implementing this act, after which he was burned in effigy by theLoyal Nine. Thomas Hutchinson’s mansion was ransacked in response to this act. Isaac Barre coinedthe term “sons of liberty” during a debate over this act, which prompted Samuel Adams to found theSons of Liberty. When this act was repealed alongside a reduced Sugar Act, Britain also passed the 1766Declaratory Act. For ten points, name this colonial tax on printed material."
    },
    {
      "number": "1.10",
      "quarter": 1,
      "answer": "Statue of Liberty (or Liberty Enlightening the World; accept La Libert´e E´clairantle Monde)",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "Edouard de Laboulaye proposed this structure as an international effort. After this structure wascompleted on Bedloe’s Island, it was celebrated with its city’s first ticker-tape parade. This monument’sbase features an Emma Lazarus poem with the verses “give me your tired, your poor, your huddledmasses” called “The New Colossus”. For ten points, name this Frederic Bartholdi-designed sculpture thatbears a copper torch in New York Harbor."
    },
    {
      "number": "1.11",
      "quarter": 1,
      "answer": "Wars of the RosesPage 2NHBB A-Set Bowl 2017-2018 Bowl Round 1",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "One leader in these conflicts saw a vision of three suns before his victory at Mortimer’s Cross. Forswitching sides in these conflicts, Richard Neville, the Earl of Warwick, was known as the Kingmaker. These conflicts ended when Richard III was defeated by Henry VII at Bosworth, ushering in the Tudordynasty. For ten points, name these conflicts between the rival English houses of Lancaster and York,named for their respective red and white flower badges."
    },
    {
      "number": "2.1",
      "quarter": 2,
      "answer": "Rwandan Genocide (accept descriptions of the genocide of the Tutsis/by the Hutusuntil “Hutu” is read)",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "Many perpetrators of this event were tried in Gacaca courts due to a backlog in the traditional justicesystem. The large number of refugees fleeing this event led to the Great Lakes Crisis in a neighboringcountry. This event was hastened by rebel forces taking Gisenyi two weeks after the Interahamwe militialost the capital city of Kigali. Paul Kagame [kuh-GAH-may] became Vice President after the end of, forten points, what 1994 event in which the Hutus massacred their Tutsi countrymen in a central Africancountry?"
    },
    {
      "number": "2.1.B",
      "quarter": 2,
      "answer": "hotels (accept Hotel des Mille Collines; accept Hotel Rwanda)",
      "is_bonus": true,
      "question": "During the Rwandan Genocide, Paul Rusesabagina protected over 1,000 refugees in one of theseestablishments."
    },
    {
      "number": "2.2",
      "quarter": 2,
      "answer": "Manfred (Albrecht Freiherr) von Richthofen (accept the Red Baron)",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "This man refused a promotion to a desk job by saying “every poor fellow in the trenches must dohis duty”. Donald Cunnel is credited with inflicting a serious head wound on this man, who attempted tokill Wilfred May but was stopped by Arthur Brown. Propaganda about this man stated the British wouldautomatically award a Victoria Cross to anyone that could kill him. The Flying Circus was led by, for tenpoints, what World War I German aviator commonly known by a colorful noble title?"
    },
    {
      "number": "2.2.B",
      "quarter": 2,
      "answer": "Hermann (Wilhelm) Goering",
      "is_bonus": true,
      "question": "After the deaths of Richthofen and Wilhelm Reinhard, command of The Flying Circus was givento this man. During World War II, this Nazi was named Reichsmarschall and commanded the Luftwaffe."
    },
    {
      "number": "2.3",
      "quarter": 2,
      "answer": "Death Valley National Park (prompt on Mojave Desert before mentioned; prompt onCalifornia before mentioned)",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "This location is home to the Timbisha Shoshone tribe, who use this location’s clay to make a red ochre[“oak-er”] paint. Accumulated salts in this location’s Badwater Basin have made its water undrinkable. In July 1913, this location’s Furnace Creek reached 134 degrees Fahrenheit, the hottest temperature everrecorded in the Western hemisphere. For ten points, name this location in the Mojave Desert of California,the lowest point in the US."
    },
    {
      "number": "2.3.B",
      "quarter": 2,
      "answer": "Herbert HooverPage 3NHBB A-Set Bowl 2017-2018 Bowl Round 1",
      "is_bonus": true,
      "question": "Death Valley was proclaimed a National Park by this President, one month before he left office. This man’s Presidential library is in West Branch, Iowa, and his home in California is now the officialresidence of the President of Stanford University."
    },
    {
      "number": "2.4",
      "quarter": 2,
      "answer": "Battle of Agincourt",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "This battle was preceded by a gift of sports balls to remind the winning king that he should stick totennis. The fall of Harfleur prompted the losing side to fight this battle. At this battle, the order to kill allprisoners was given after Henry V feared that his baggage train would be overrun. This battle’s losing sidecould not use cavalry thanks to stakes placed in muddy ground; instead the winning side’s longbowmenfired at will. For ten points, name this 1415 battle fought on St. Crispin’s Day, a victory for England inthe Hundred Years’ War."
    },
    {
      "number": "2.4.B",
      "quarter": 2,
      "answer": "Battle of Crecy",
      "is_bonus": true,
      "question": "The English longbow also played a big role in this 1346 battle, where it prevailed over Genoesecrossbows. Shortly after this battle, Calais [cah-lay] fell to England."
    },
    {
      "number": "2.5",
      "quarter": 2,
      "answer": "Prohibition (accept temperance; prompt on 18th Amendment or Volstead Act before eachis mentioned)",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "This policy was largely ignored by Congress as senators flocked to buy from “the man in thegreen-hat,” George Cassiday. Neal Dow became one of the first mayors to implement this policy underthe Maine Law. Contraband violating this policy was destroyed by a hatchet-wielding Carrie Nation fromthe WCTU. This policy became law when the Volstead Act was enacted to carry out the EighteenthAmendment. For ten points, name this 1920s policy that banned liquor throughout the US."
    },
    {
      "number": "2.5.B",
      "quarter": 2,
      "answer": "Alphonse “Al” Capone",
      "is_bonus": true,
      "question": "During Prohibition, this leader of the Chicago Outfit, known as Scarface, made massive profitssmuggling alcohol."
    },
    {
      "number": "2.6",
      "quarter": 2,
      "answer": "The Canterbury Tales",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "In an unfinished story from this collection, Canace finds a falcon who was abandoned by her lover andthen shows a romantic interest in her brother, who is also Genghis Khan’s son. In this collection’s firststory, Palamon and Arcite fight in a massive battle to win Emily’s hand in marraige. Characters in thiswork include the Squire and his father, the Knight, who tell stories during their pilgrimage to the shrineof Thomas Becket. For ten points, name this story collection by Geoffrey Chaucer."
    },
    {
      "number": "2.6.B",
      "quarter": 2,
      "answer": "Middle English (prompt on English)Page 4NHBB A-Set Bowl 2017-2018 Bowl Round 1",
      "is_bonus": true,
      "question": "Geoffrey Chaucer wrote The Canterbury Tales in this language, which was in use fromapproximately the Norman conquest of Britain through the 16th century."
    },
    {
      "number": "2.7",
      "quarter": 2,
      "answer": "Battle of the Bulge (accept Operation Watch on the Rhine or Wacht am Rhein; acceptArdennes Counteroffensive before “Ardennes” is read)",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "This battle’s Operation Griffin included a violation of the Hague Convention when Otto Skorzenydressed his troops in enemy uniforms. During this battle, American troops were fired on after surrenderingat Malmedy. Anthony McAuliffe led a spirited defense of the town of Bastogne in this battle, whose losingside tried to use tanks to recreate the 1941 invasion of France. For ten points, name this 1944 battle thatmade a namesake shape in Allied lines."
    },
    {
      "number": "2.7.B",
      "quarter": 2,
      "answer": "George S. Patton",
      "is_bonus": true,
      "question": "The siege of Bastogne was lifted by this American commander of the Third Army. He was brieflydisgraced for slapping a shell-shocked soldier during the Sicily landings."
    },
    {
      "number": "2.8",
      "quarter": 2,
      "answer": "lung cancer",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "A type of this disease that makes surgery difficult was discovered by Henry Pancoast. Fritz Lickintexperimented with X-raying the spleen as a cure for this disease and coined the term for a “passive” causeof it. Scientists in Nazi Germany discovered the link between this disease and asbestos. In the late 1990s,Philip Morris admitted that its products cause this disease. For ten points, name this type of cancer oftencaused by smoking tobacco."
    },
    {
      "number": "2.8.B",
      "quarter": 2,
      "answer": "second-hand smoke (accept word forms)",
      "is_bonus": true,
      "question": "This term for smoke inhaled by non-smokers developed out of Fritz Lickint’s theories about thedangers of “passive smoking”. Governments have cited the dangers of this type of environmental exposureto smoke when passing laws banning smoking in public."
    },
    {
      "number": "3.1",
      "quarter": 3,
      "answer": "United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland (accept Great Britain; accept England)",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "First country the US declared war on, doing so in 1812."
    },
    {
      "number": "3.2",
      "quarter": 3,
      "answer": "Commander-in-Chief (do not prompt on commander alone)",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "Military title assigned to the President in the Constitution as head of the armed forces."
    },
    {
      "number": "3.3",
      "quarter": 3,
      "answer": "Article 2 of the US Constitution",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "Article of the Constitution that details the President’s powers and roles, including that title."
    },
    {
      "number": "3.4",
      "quarter": 3,
      "answer": "Guantanamo Bay Naval Base (accept Gitmo)",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "Cuban naval base used by the US to detain terror suspects and enemy combatants."
    },
    {
      "number": "3.5",
      "quarter": 3,
      "answer": "War Powers Act (or Resolution, Law, etc.)",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "Controversial 1973 law that restricts the President’s power to deploy armed troops beyond 60 days."
    },
    {
      "number": "3.6",
      "quarter": 3,
      "answer": "writ of habeas corpus",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "Writ that prevents unlawful detention but was suspended unlawfully by Abraham Lincoln during theCivil War."
    },
    {
      "number": "3.7",
      "quarter": 3,
      "answer": "Kosovo",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "Former Yugoslavian country, unrecognized by Serbia, whose 1999 bombing led Tom Campbell to sueBill Clinton."
    },
    {
      "number": "3.8",
      "quarter": 3,
      "answer": "Youngstown Sheet and Tube Company vs. Sawyer (accept Youngstown Steel case; acceptSteel Seizure case)Page 6NHBB A-Set Bowl 2017-2018 Bowl Round 1Soviet UnionName the...",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "1952 Supreme Court case that limited President Truman’s ability to seize private property duringwar."
    },
    {
      "number": "3.9",
      "quarter": 3,
      "answer": "Russia (or Russian Federation)",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "Successor state to the Soviet Union whose capital is Moscow."
    },
    {
      "number": "3.10",
      "quarter": 3,
      "answer": "Joseph Vissarionovich Stalin",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "Dictator who ordered the death of Leon Trotsky and was succeeded by Nikita Khrushchev."
    },
    {
      "number": "3.11",
      "quarter": 3,
      "answer": "arsaw Pact(accepttheTreaty of Friendship, Cooperation, and Mutual Assistance)",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "Soviet-led counterpart of NATO, composed of Eastern Bloc countries."
    },
    {
      "number": "3.12",
      "quarter": 3,
      "answer": "Hungary",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "European country where the Soviets crushed Imre Nagy’s [nahj’s] rebellion in 1956."
    },
    {
      "number": "3.13",
      "quarter": 3,
      "answer": "Kitchen Debate",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "1959 event in which Nixon and Khrushchev debated capitalism and communism in a model home."
    },
    {
      "number": "3.14",
      "quarter": 3,
      "answer": "Holodomor",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "Genocidal famine in Ukraine from 1932-33."
    },
    {
      "number": "3.15",
      "quarter": 3,
      "answer": "SALT 1 and/or 2 (or Strategic Arms Limitation Talks)",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "Name for both US-Soviet treaties that limited ballistic missile production."
    },
    {
      "number": "3.16",
      "quarter": 3,
      "answer": "Kronstadt RebellionPage 7NHBB A-Set Bowl 2017-2018 Bowl Round 1Ancient EgyptName the...",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "1921 rebellion whose suppression led to the development of the New Economic Policy."
    },
    {
      "number": "3.17",
      "quarter": 3,
      "answer": "pharaoh",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "Title given to the rulers of ancient Egypt."
    },
    {
      "number": "3.18",
      "quarter": 3,
      "answer": "Nile River",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "Primary Egyptian river that flooded during the season of Akhet."
    },
    {
      "number": "3.19",
      "quarter": 3,
      "answer": "King Tutankhamun",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "Boy king whose tomb was re-discovered by Howard Carter in 1922."
    },
    {
      "number": "3.20",
      "quarter": 3,
      "answer": "Rosetta Stone",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "Stone dedicated to Ptolemy V that was used to decipher hieroglyphics."
    },
    {
      "number": "3.21",
      "quarter": 3,
      "answer": "Battle of Kadesh",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "1274 BC battle against the Hittites, the largest chariot battle in history."
    },
    {
      "number": "3.22",
      "quarter": 3,
      "answer": "Egyptian Book of the Dead",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "Document that provides instructions for those being judged by Ma’at."
    },
    {
      "number": "3.23",
      "quarter": 3,
      "answer": "Abu Simbel",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "Massive rock temples of Ramesses the Great and Nefertari built in Nubia."
    },
    {
      "number": "3.24",
      "quarter": 3,
      "answer": "Smenkhare (or Smenkhkare)Page 8NHBB A-Set Bowl 2017-2018 Bowl Round 1",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "Ruler who briefly succeeded Akhenaten, but who may actually just have been Nefertiti disguised as aman."
    },
    {
      "number": "4.2",
      "quarter": 4,
      "answer": "Presidential Election of 1980 (prompt on 80)",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "In this election year, the “Draft Muskie” movement emerged to break a deadlockedconvention. John B. Anderson ran as an independent in this election. Controversy from the(+) Chappaquiddick incident 11 years earlier damaged Ted Kennedy’s chances of beingnominated during this year. Despite the “voodoo economics” attack in this year’s primaries,(*) George H.W. Bush was nominated for Vice President. The failure to resolve the Iran Hostage Crisishelped doom a re-election campaign in, for ten points, what year in which Jimmy Carter lost 44 states toRonald Reagan?"
    },
    {
      "number": "4.3",
      "quarter": 4,
      "answer": "Bolivarian Republic of Venezuela",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "This modern day country was briefly mortgaged in the 16th century to a Germanbanking family whose sons wanted to search for the Fountain of Youth. This country’s cityof Coro is one of the oldest European cities founded in the Americas. This country, whichwas named for (+) stilted houses in lagoons that reminded Spanish colonists of a Europeancity, is officially a “Bolivarian Republic” to commemorate (*) Simon Bolivar, who was born here. For ten points, name this country where Spanish colonists founded cities like Maracaibo and Caracas."
    },
    {
      "number": "4.4",
      "quarter": 4,
      "answer": "Hamilton: An American Musical (accept “Alexander Hamilton” before “French” is read)",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "An early version of this work uses the phrase “waiting in the weeds,” later changedto “waiting in the wings”. In this work, a boy sings in French, then recites a poem on hisninth (+) birthday to his father. The protagonist of this work is told to “talk less” and“smile more” by the antagonist, who later laments that “the world was (*) wide enough” forboth himself and the title character after they duel at Weehawken. For ten points, name this Lin-ManuelMiranda musical about the first treasury secretary, who was killed in a duel with Aaron Burr."
    },
    {
      "number": "4.5",
      "quarter": 4,
      "answer": "Hanseatic League (accept Hansa)",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "This group formed the Confederation of Cologne and conducted a bombardment ofCopenhagen, forcing Valdemar IV to grant them increased privileges. This group wasplagued by the forces of Albert of Mecklenburg and the (+) Victual Brothers, and itsuffered a setback when Ivan III shut down their operations in Novgorod. This group wasprominent in Bergen and Stralsund, but it was dominated by (*) Lu¨beck in its early stages. Aseries of kontor trading posts was administered by, for ten points, what Northern European merchantsguild formed during the Late Middle Ages?"
    },
    {
      "number": "4.6",
      "quarter": 4,
      "answer": "goldPage 9NHBB A-Set Bowl 2017-2018 Bowl Round 1",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "Domitian added the purple faction and a faction named for this material to chariotraces. A palace on the future site of the Colosseum built by Nero was known as the houseof this material. When Heinrich (+) Schliemann discovered an artifact of this material inMycenae, it convinced him he found the body of a legendary Homeric king. This material,which is combined with (*) ivory to make chryselephantine sculptures, was used to mint a coin worth25 denarii [day-NAR-ee-ee] called the aureus. The funeral mask of Agamemnon is made of, for ten points,what yellowish precious metal?"
    },
    {
      "number": "4.7",
      "quarter": 4,
      "answer": "Texas",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "Thomas Van Orden sued this state in 2002 to take down a display of the TenCommandments; the case was argued at the Supreme Court by this state’s AttorneyGeneral, who became Governor after defeating pro-choice State Senator Wendy (+) Davisin 2014. The previous governor of this state currently serves as head of the Department ofEnergy, a department that he proposed to eliminate in his 2012 presidential bid. Anotherformer governor of this state promoted the (*) No Child Left Behind Act after he was electedpresident in 2000. For ten points, name this state that has been governed by Greg Abbott, Rick Perry,and George W. Bush."
    },
    {
      "number": "4.8",
      "quarter": 4,
      "answer": "Treaty (or Peace, etc.) of Utrecht",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "Hostilities that this treaty failed to end were later resolved through the Treaties of Badenand Rastatt. Under this treaty, 200 years after Tordesillas, Portugal’s control of Brazil wasfinally recognized. Great Britain gained (+) Gibraltar and the asiento, a monopoly onthe slave trade, through this treaty. Under this treaty, a claim to the (*) French throne wasrenounced by Philip of Anjou so that he could be king of an Iberian country. For ten points, name thistreaty that ended the War of Spanish Succession."
    },
    {
      "number": "4.9",
      "quarter": 4,
      "answer": "Daniel Webster",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "This man claimed New England was not guilty of an intent to dissolve the Union in aspeech against James Monroe’s conscription plan. Following John Tyler’s decision to breakwith party lines, this man was the only member of Tyler’s (+) cabinet not to resign. Ina reply to Robert Hayne, this man declared that the US government was “made (*) forthe people, made by the people, and answerable to the people”. For ten points, name this Massachusettssenator who said “Liberty and Union, now and forever, one and inseparable! ”"
    }
  ],
  "categories": ["American War", "Soviet Union", "Ancient Egypt"]

}